Mike Dougherty

Code Whisperer and Remodeler

Contact Info

Phone: 858.232.3635

• Email: miked@threedev.io

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/mikedougherty/

Summary

Mike is currently a Lead Code Whisperer at Corgibytes and has almost 30 years of experience in software engineering and consulting and has led numerous large-scale and multi-year projects in a wide variety of technology stacks and cloud-based infrastructure. He enjoys working collaboratively with teams to solve complex problems, whether they are related to stabilizing and refactoring legacy code, re-architecting application components, or finding better ways to test, build and deploy with modern tooling.

Experience

Lead Code Whisperer

Corgibytes, Richmond, VA May 2019 - Present

- As a member of the team working on Shelterluv's Drupal 7 based application, Mike helped modernize, detangle and apply the Strangler Pattern to prepare them for rapid development and deployment as they target a Macroservice Architecture for the future of the application.
- As a member of the team working to help Capital One Financial (COF) modernize their Java and Scala microservices to reduce code complexity and duplication and migrate to new CI/CD pipelines and code analysis tools and requirements.

Senior Consultant / Architect

Three Dev, San Diego, CA 2003 - Present Architect, develop and maintain custom software solutions for various clients in Java, Objective-C and other languages..

- Developed assorted Java EE (JSF, EJB, JPA) applications including WaveReg.com and thelifeapp.us.
- Developed iOS and Android applications iForget, Horizon, Rock Mobile.
- Developed Java EE Mogiv SMS and online donation platform mogiv.com.

Software Developer

Itdesign, GmBH, Tübingen, Germany 2014 - 2017

- Develop, debug and support GWT/GXT application itd: Assignment Editor and itd: Allocation Editor.
- Scrum Product Owner for itd: Assignment Editor, itd: Allocation Editor and other PPM products.
- Project manager for U.S. customers and projects.

Java Architect / Engineer

iBASEt, Inc. San Diego, CA 2004 - 2006

• Architecture, design, and development of FORCEnet Implementation Tool Suite (FITS) and Ship Maintenance Process Java EE applications.

Senior Java Engineer

XIFIN, Inc. San Diego, CA 2002 - 2004

- Designed and Implemented MVC (Model View Controller) framework for use in Swing applications.
- Rewrite of Order Entry as Web application using Struts MVC framework.
- Architecture and design of Laboratory Order and Reporting (LOR).

Lead Java Engineer

Cogenisys, Inc., San Diego, CA

2001 - 2002

- Develop runnable Java EE application by applying industry design patterns to UML model.
- Develop XSL templates for generating runnable Java EE application from UML model.

Lead Java Engineer

Aradiant Corporation, San Diego, CA 2001 - 2001

- Analyzed current dispatch program, operator agent uses and needs, to gather requirements.
- Developed proof of concept and prototype with J2EE and Swing technologies.

Lead Java Engineer

Teradata CRM, San Diego, CA 2000 - 2001

- Designed and developed adapter factory to turn user expressions into Java byte code.
- Designed and developed framework for rules engine processing.

Java Engineer

MediaDNA Inc., San Diego, CA 1999 - 2000

- Assisted in the design and development of the DRM system
- Designed and developed customer service and administration application for the DRM system

Java Engineer

MessageMedia Inc. (formerly First Virtual Holdings Inc.), San Diego, CA 1995 - 1999

- Design, develop and maintain web administration console for the IMC (Interactive Messaging Center)
- Administration, research and support for the VirtualPIN transaction platform

Skills

Languages/Markup: Java EE, Groovy, PHP, HTML5, CSS, Objective-C, XML, XSL

Data/ETL: MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, NoSQL (i.e. MongoDB, Datastore/Firestore, etc)

Infrastructure/Cloud/DevOps: GCP, AWS, Jenkins, BitBucket Pipelines, Linux, macOS, Unix

Frameworks: JPA/Hibernate, JSF/JSP, Spring, Struts, Laravel, Codelgniter, GWT, Android, iOS

Web Services: REST, SAML, SOAP, XMLRPC, OAuth **SDLC**: Agile, SCRUM, Kanban, TDD, BDD, Jira, Trello

Education

Business Administration and Management

University of Redlands, San Diego, CA

Level 1 Information Assurance Training & Level 3 Unix System Administrator *SAIC Inc., San Diego, CA*

B1 Language Certification in German

Bundesamt für Migration und Flüchtlinge, Tübingen, Germany